Okay, so good afternoon. So today's דף daf is למד ט' Lamed
Tet and we pick up at the bottom of למד ז' עמוד
ב' Lamed Zayin Amud Bet
and it's תנן התם. Tnan Hatam. It's about ten lines from the
bottom, three lines after the גמרא Gemara begins after the משנה. Mishnah.
So we taught over there in מנחות Menachot because the משנה Mishnah
mentioned
the
waving of the לולב lulav and it speaks about waving it at
different points in the הלל, Hallel, הודו לה' Hodu Lashem at the
beginning and at the end, and אנא ה' הושיעה נא. Ana Hashem
Hoshia Na. According to בית שמאי, Beit Shammai, אנא ה' הצליחה נא.
Ana Hashem Hatzlicha Na. תוספות Tosafot brought in a very beautiful explanation
linking it to פסוקים psukim in דברי הימים Divrei Hayamim which speaks
about the trees of the forest bursting out in song and then
it says the actual פסוקים psukim of הודו לה' כי טוב Hodu
Lashem Ki Tov and הושיענו אלוהי ישענו. Hoshienu Elohei Yishenu. So seeing
that that is being connected to the shaking of the לולב lulav
like the trees bursting out in song and then with the connection
of the הודו לה' Hodu Lashem and the אנא ה' הושיעה נא.
Ana Hashem Hoshia Na. So that, and then there was also the
question of exactly our practice that it's not just the הודו לה'
Hodu Lashem initially but that the שליח ציבור shliach tzibur does it
with the יאמר נא ישראל, Yomar Na Yisrael, יאמר נא בית אהרן
Yomar Na Beit Aharon and then the ציבור tzibur responds with הודו
לה'. Hodu Lashem. So תוספות Tosafot also discussed exactly how that becomes
our current practice of the waving of the לולב lulav during הלל.
Hallel. So now the גמרא Gemara connects this idea of waving with
another aspect of some of the waving. Let's take a look. תנן
התם, Tnan Hatam, so we taught over there in מנחות. Menachot. שתי
הלחם ושני כבשי עצרת. Shtei Halechem Ushnei Kivsei Atzeret.
When you have on שבועות Shavuot the two loaves of bread that
you would bring of the newly cut wheat and the two lambs
that would be brought for that קרבן. korban. כיצד הוא עושה, Keitzad
Hu Oseh, what do you do when you wave it? Because it
says that it's waved, the loaves with the lambs. So מניח שתי
הלחם על גבי שני הכבשים, Maniach Shtei Halechem Al Gabei Shenei Hakvasim,
you put the loaves on top of the lambs, ומניח ידיו תחתיהן
Umaniach Yadav Tachtehen
and you put your hands underneath them, ומניף ומוליך ומביא מעלה ומוריד.
Umanif Umolich Umavi Maaleh Umorid.
So you wave it and you bring it front and back and
up and down. שנאמר, Shene'emar, as the verse says, אשר הונף ואשר
הורם, Asher Hunaf Vaasher Huram,
that was waved and that was lifted up. Now that's not exactly
a פסוק pasuk by the שתי הלחם Shtei Halechem but it is
a פסוק pasuk about certain תנופה tnufa waving that you do in
the בית המקדש Beit Hamikdash and therefore we are assuming that it
is the same type of a waving that is done here. Okay,
so let's take and that's by the bread of the מילואים miluim
when the כהנים kohanim were initiated into the בית המקדש. Beit Hamikdash.
So what does that mean? So אמר רבי יוחנן, Amar Rabbi Yochanan,
מוליך ומביא molich umavi למי שארבע רוחות שלו. lemi she'arba ruchot shelo.
So the idea of הונף hunaf waving, he says means bringing in
and bringing out, מוליך ומביא molich umavi and that is to the
one to whom the four winds belong to him, meaning for God's
sake. So presumably מוליך ומביא molich umavi to bring out and bring
in could mean like to put in front of you and then
to pull back into you. It could also mean like to your
right and to your left and since it mentions the four winds
of the, you know, the four directions, presumably it's both. It's bringing
in and out and front and back
and
מעלה ומוריד maaleh umorid and then you bring up and down למי
שהשמים והארץ שלו. lemi sheshamayim va'aretz shelo. So it's interesting, right? Because
he said only מוליך ומביא molich umavi but it has four directions.
The משנה Mishnah said, what's the משנה Mishnah said? מניף ומוליך ומביא.
manif umolich umavi. So you wave it and מוליך ומביא. molich umavi.
So in the in the משנה Mishnah that they quoted, מניף manif
might be to the right and the left and מוליך ומביא molich
umavi front and back, but there is clearly this sense of all
four directions and up and down. Okay, that's אשר הונף ואשר הורם.
Asher Hunaf Vaasher Huram. Now במערבא, bamaarava,
so that's the waving of the lambs and the bread. In ארץ
ישראל Eretz Yisrael מתנו הכי, matnu hachi, they taught this way.
אמר רבי חמא בר עוקבא אמר רבי יוסי ברבי חנינא, Amar Rabbi
Chama bar Ukva Amar Rabbi Yose bar Rabbi Chanina,
מוליך ומביא, molich umavi, you bring it front and back and again
also probably to the sides כדי לעצור רוחות רעות kedei la'atzor ruchot
ra'ot
in order to hold back, to prevent the bad winds. I don't
know if anybody tried walking just this morning, that was really bad
wind. מעלה ומוריד maaleh umorid up and down כדי לעצור טללים רעים
kedei la'atzor tlalim ra'im to hold back the bad rains. It's quite
interesting, it's not necessarily to bring good but to hold back the
bad, to ward off the bad. Now this is all by the
שתי הלחם. Shtei Halechem. What is the direct connection to the לולב?
lulav? We'll talk in a minute. Let's read a little bit more
in the גמרא. Gemara. אמר רבי יוסי בר אבין ואיתימא רבי יוסי
בר זבדא, Amar Rabbi Yose bar Avin ve'itayma Rabbi Yose bar Zavda,
זאת אומרת, Zot omeret, this teaches you שירי מצוה מעכבין את הפורענות
shiyarei mitzvah me'akvin et hapuranut
that the even the remnants of the מצוה, mitzvah, meaning the waving,
because if you didn't do the waving you're still יוצא yotzei your
קרבן korban but it's an important part of bringing the קרבן korban
but it's not... a necessary part. And therefore it's called the like
the remnants of the מצוה. mitzvah. So even the smaller even those
remnants of the מצוה mitzvah they prevent bad things from happening because
the whole point of the waving according to this is to stop
the bad winds and the bad rains. שהרי תנופה שירי מצוה היא,
Sheharei tnufah shirei mitzvah hi, the waving is a remnant of a
מצוה, mitzvah, ועוצרת רוחות וטללים רעים, ve'otzeret ruchot utlalim ra'im,
and it holds back bad winds and bad rains. ואמר רבא, Ve'amar
Rava, now here is why it's being brought in, וכן בלולב, vechein
balulav,
the same thing is with לולב. lulav. Now, does he mean the
same significance? Not necessarily. The direct application if you look at רש"י
Rashi is וכן בלולב מוליך ומביא מעלה ומוריד, vechein balulav molich umeivi
ma'aleh umorid, that this is telling you how to do the waving.
The waving is like you would do this way, you know, to
the four directions and then up and down. רב אחא בר יעקב
מנפי ליה ומייתי ליה. Rav Acha bar Yaakov manfi lei umaytei lei.
So רב אחא בר יעקב Rav Acha bar Yaakov would,
you know, bring it out and bring it in. That's like the
מוליך ומביא. molich umeivi. So okay, I mean, that's pretty much what
רבא Rava said, but presumably the point is not just what he'd
do this, but he would say אמר, amar, one who would bring
it out and in, he'd say דין גירא בעיניה דסטנא. dein gira
be'einei desitna.
This is like a,
you know, a spear in the eyes of the שטן. Satan. So
he'd bring it out, he'd like be poking, he's like saying I'm
poking the eyes of the שטן Satan as he protrudes it out.
ולאו ניחותא היא, Velav nichuta hi, that's not, you shouldn't be doing
that, משום דאתי לאגרויי ביה. mishum de'ati le'agruyei beih. You know, you
don't want to provoke the שטן. Satan. You don't want to say
ha, back at you שטן, Satan, then you'll, then you'll get him
interested in you and it's actually going to make more problems rather
than do anything good. Now, it is interesting here a couple of
things. First of all, you know, the comparison to the שתי הלחם
shetei halechem in addition to just sort of saying well that's what
we mean, you know, where is this whole idea of נענועים nanu'im
coming from? Like where did we even get this idea that you
do נענועים nanu'im with the לולב? lulav? It says ולקחתם לכם. ulekachtem
lachem. So you could say maybe ולקחתם ulekachtem means like a vigorous
taking, as in take it and really seize it, you know, but
it doesn't sound like that. The whole context of the הלל Hallel
and the waving of it in a religious context. So what the
גמרא Gemara is doing is the גמרא Gemara is introducing a model
for this. You know, where actually we have this model of a
waving that is done in a religious context, and that's presumably what
this is being modeled after. So again that is significant because that
is once again connecting the ארבע מינים arba minim and the לולב
lulav and the אתרוג etrog to the world of קרבנות, korbanot, a
point that we have made multiple times before, that the way it's
being made into something like a קרבן. korban. And here, even before
you get to the symbolism, the whole idea that you do a
waving, the גמרא Gemara never gives a source for it. תוספות Tosafot
again speaks about the leaves, the trees of the forest bursting out
in song, but again being connected to an area where you actually
do wave this object before God. Now it actually goes beyond that
because if you think about it and this is a point that
תוספות Tosafot makes, when you wave the שתי הלחם, shetei halechem, what
are you waving? You're waving the new grain. And you also, right,
and that
is, and that's like what's new agriculturally at the time of שבועות
Shavuot is the new grain. Well what's new agriculturally at the time
of סוכות? Sukkot? It's the ארבע מינים. arba minim. This represents, right,
all of the produce of the field that you're gathering in. So
think about what we've just done. We've taken this agricultural aspect of
the חג chag and the same way we wave it on שבועות,
Shavuot, we're waving it on סוכות. Sukkot. So it's not just a
random model, there's a very strong power of the parallel.
And if you so if you take a לולב lulav he says
like this he says,
so תוספות Tosafot says כדי לעצור רוחות רעות. kedei la'atzor ruchot ra'ot.
So it says it says בפרק כל המנחות באות מצה, bepherek kol
hamenachot ba'ot matzah, חשיב כל הטעונים תנופה, chashiv kol hate'unim tnufah, ושמא
לא בכל תנופה עושים כן. veshama lo bechol tnufah osim ken.
Maybe why do we mention דוקא davka the שתי הלחם? shetei halechem?
There's a lot of תנופות tnufot that you do. You know what,
maybe all the other תנופות tnufot are not done in the exact
same way. אלא דוקא בתנופת שתי הלחם דעצרת, ela davka bitnufat shetei
halechem de'atzeret, וכן לולב. vechein lulav. Maybe it's only by the שתי
הלחם shetei halechem that you do it in all these directions and
also we apply it to לולב lulav משום דאמרינן פרק קמא דראש
השנה, mishum de'amrinan perek kama deRosh Hashanah, גזר דין נחתם בפסח על
התבואה ובעצרת על פירות האילן ובחג, gezar din nechtam bePesach al hatvu'ah
uve'atzeret al peirot ha'ilan uvachag, ובחג על המים. uvachag al hamayim.
So every every holiday has a different
גזר דין, gezar din, right, and on שבועות Shavuot on the fruit,
and on סוכות Sukkot on the water. ולכן אנו מנענעים בלולב שיש
בו הולכה והבאה ulachen anu menan'im balulav sheyesh bo holachah vehava'ah in
order to, you know, in order to be a type of a
תפילה tefillah for the rain. Okay, so תוספות Tosafot says maybe there's
a
specifically only these type of waving you only find by שבועות Shavuot
and we're applying it to סוכות Sukkot and he makes this comparison
about what is the purpose. If you see it as a type
of a יום הדין yom hadin and you need a special prayer
for, you know, like the גמרא Gemara says, the rain and the
wind and what's going to affect, you know, the what's going to
affect you agriculturally. So there's a יום הדין yom hadin aspect for
סוכות Sukkot as well which is the rain, which is, excuse me,
which is the rain, and we actually mention the bad rains, maybe
bad rains were a problem שבועות Shavuos time, here we want good
rains, so it's a type of a waving and a using, you
know, and you use these lush things maybe to represent, you know,
the need of rain and things that grow on rain, and you
do it in that way. So connecting it again in that way,
I would say beyond the יום הדין Yom HaDin aspect, you know,
you can connect it also to just a sense of שמחה simcha
of gratitude and again I think that there's even a stronger comparison
that you take the product of the new wheat on שבועות Shavuos
and you wave it and you take sort of the products of
the fields that's been drying or whatever that represents, you know, the
gathering in and you wave that as well. So there really is,
it's not just a technical point here but there's actually a strong
suggestion of this comparison and again connecting it to the world of
קרבנות. korbanos. So that is one thing. The other thing I'll just
mention
is
the original statement of רב יוחנן, Rav Yochanan, you do it sort
of to God, right, without sort of saying that it's a prayer
for something, for holding back the bad rains, holding back the bad
wind, etc. it's just for God. In a way this also represents
two symbolisms of the לולב. lulav. I think I might have mentioned
this before. There's a מדרש Midrash again, it's not in the גמרא,
Gemara, it's probably later so question exactly how early it is. But
there's a מדרש Midrash about רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva that he sees
the ארבע מינים Arba Minim representing God. הלולב זו הקדוש ברוך הוא,
אתרוג זו הקדוש ברוך הוא, ha-lulav zu ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu, esrog zu
ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu, like everything is הקדוש ברוך הוא. ha-Kadosh Baruch Hu.
He also says there's only one of each of the מינים minim
which might be connected. So, you know, one idea is just it
represents God, it represents our connection to God, we're holding and we're
shaking and it somehow represents our connection to God. Whereas the other
approach says it's a prayer to God, you use it to pray,
you know, but that's the more general understanding is you take the
ארבע מינים Arba Minim as a way to pray for the good
rains, right, and it's a vehicle for this type of a prayer
and that also connects more to the second interpretation here which sees
it not as being directly to God but about being a prayer
for the agricultural, for the weather, and so on. The very, again,
I don't know exactly what to do about the connection to poking
out the eyes of the שטן, Satan, unless again it's connected, that
maybe is connecting it less to the agricultural aspects of סוכות Sukkos
and maybe back to it being a culmination of the יום הדין.
Yom HaDin. So we do have a mention in the גמרא Gemara
of שטן, Satan, like the גמרא Gemara says why do we sit
and stand by the blowing of the שופר, shofar, you know, because
לערבב את השטן, l'arbev es ha-Satan, to confuse the שטן. Satan. So
the גמרא Gemara actually does have a heightened mention, the גמרא Gemara
doesn't mention the שטן Satan too much, but it has a heightened
mention of it around the ימים נוראים. Yamim Noraim. So speaking about
this poking out the eyes of the שטן Satan might be sort
of situating this more as the type of a culmination of the
עשרת ימי תשובה Aseret Yemei Teshuva and the ימי הדין. Yemei HaDin.
So interesting to see the three different symbolisms that come up and
also the comparison to the world of קרבנות korbanos and the comparison
to שבועות. Shavuos. The last thing I'll just say is that תוספות
Tosafos has a whole question about how do you, you know, the
ירושלמי Yerushalmi that says you do it three times. And how do
you count the three? Do you say out is one and in
is two? Or out and in is one? Do you out and
in and out and in three times, right? So that's one question
he asks if you have to do it three. And then another
thing which he doesn't ask but that gets asked is, you know,
some people do it like out and do three times over here
and in this three times here and then three times here as
opposed to doing this three times. How do you count the three
times? Anyway, our גמרא Gemara doesn't say three times but it does
come up in the ירושלמי Yerushalmi and then there becomes all these
different questions as how exactly you do the counting. Okay, so that
was a very fascinating in terms of where comparing it to that
which might be the source of the idea of shaking, maybe the
verse that תוספות Tosafos quotes, אז ירננו עצי היער, az yeranenu atzei
ha-ya'ar, but where do we get this idea from? And then all
these different possible symbolisms and connections to שבועות. Shavuos. Now we take
a look at the next משנה mishna because again it's quite fascinating
a point I want to get back to that it's mentioning all
this shaking and during הלל, Hallel, and it didn't start with the
simple idea of just taking the לולב lulav and that's the מצוה.
mitzvah. You make the ברכה, beracha, you take the לולב. lulav. So
let's take a look at this next משנה mishna which brings us
into that. So it says: מי שבא בדרך ולא היה בידו לולב.
Mi she-ba baderech v'lo hayah b'yado lulav. Somebody who came from back
from a journey and he didn't have a לולב, lulav, he didn't
travel, he didn't have a traveling
לולב. lulav. What do you do?
לכשיכנס לביתו יטול על שלחנו. L'kshe-yikanes l'veito yitol al shulchano. When he
gets into his house, take it on the table. It's a funny
thing on the table, what does that mean? The גמרא's Gemara going
to say it means even interrupt a meal to take it. Okay,
but there's also a חידוש chiddush before you get to the idea
of interrupt a meal, there seems to be a חידוש chiddush here
that you take it in the house as opposed to taking it
where? Meaning where would be the natural place to take it?
I think as they mentioned
in the בית כנסת Beit Knesset when you're doing the הלל Hallel
and doing the shaking, right? I think that is implied, that the
first introduction to taking the לולב, lulav, it talks about the shaking
of
it in
הלל, Hallel, which clearly... ברכה bracha *bracha* they take it at home
and then they bring it to שול shul. *shul*. And how much
is there an idea of taking it independent of the idea of
the נענועי *nanuey*? I want to get back to that but let's
first finish reading this.
Maybe he should be דאוונינג davening, *davening* הלל Hallel, *Hallel* at home
by sunrise. Okay.
דלא הוה בי *D'lo hayo bi* now. יטול על שולחנו *Yitol al
shulchano*, לא נטלה שחרית shacharis, *lo natla Shacharis*, יטול בין הערביים *yitol
bayn haarbayim*, שכל היום כשר ללולב *shekol hayom kasher l'lulav*,
even though you normally take it in the morning when you say
שחרית *Shacharis* and when you say הלל Hallel, *Hallel*, you can really
take it the whole day. Okay, so the point of this simple
point of this משנה Mishna *Mishna* seems to be even if you
didn't do it the right time in the morning or the right
context in שול shul *shul* and in הלל Hallel, *Hallel*, you can
still take it independent of that time and context as long as
you do it sometime during the day. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says the following. אמרת ניטול על שולחנו *Amarta nital al shulchano*, you
say take it on your table. למימרא דמפסיק *L'maimra d'mafsik*? That sounds
like you interrupt your meal. והא רמיניהו *Veha raminihu*, I'll ask you
on this: אם התחילו אין מפסיקין *im hitchilu ain mafsikin*, there's a
משנה Mishna *Mishna* by דאוונינג מנחה Mincha, *davening Mincha* that it says
in שבת *Shabbos* that you should not start certain activities, go and
getting a haircut and other types of things or sitting down for
a meal before דאוונינג מנחה Mincha. *davening Mincha*, but if you did
you don't interrupt your meal and you don't have to get up
from the barber's in order to דאוון *daven* if you actually started
it. So why there do you not have to interrupt and here
you do have to interrupt? So אמר רב ספרא לא קשיא *Amar
Rav Safra lo kashya*, it's not difficult. הא דאיכא שהות ביום הא
דליכא שהות ביום *Ha d'ika sha'os bayom, ha d'leika sha'os bayom*. You
don't have to interrupt if there's time in the day to still
get it done. That's the משנה Mishna's *Mishna* by here. Here when
we'd say interrupt your meal we mean if you're afraid that by
the time you finish your meal it will already be night and
you'll run out of time, that's when you do have to interrupt.
Okay, that's reasonable. אמר רבא Amar Rava, *Amar Rava*, says רבא Rava.
*Rava*: מאי קושיא *mai kushya*? I didn't understand the question to begin
with. דאמר הא דאורייתא הא דרבנן derabbanan *D'omar ha d'Oraisa ha d'Rabbanan*.
When it says don't interrupt for to דאוון מנחה *daven Mincha*, that's
because דאוונינג מנחה *davening Mincha* is דרבנן *Rabbinic*, right? I mean maybe
there's an idea to דאוון *daven* once a day דאורייתא *d'Oraisa* but
it's certainly not the specific text of חז"ל Chazal *Chazal*, it's certainly
not specifically שחרית מנחה ומעריב *Shacharis, Mincha, and Maariv*, that's clearly דרבנן
*Rabbinic*. So therefore you don't interrupt if you're already started something to
do a דרבנן *Rabbinic* מצוה Mitzvah? *mitzvah*. But the taking the לולב
lulav *lulav*, that's a biblical מצוה Mitzvah. *mitzvah*. So I don't even
understand what bothered you why you thought it was a question. So
אלא אמר רבא Rava *Ella Amar Rava*, so רבא Rava, *Rava* says
no. אי קשיא הא קשיא *I kushya ha kushya*. If there was
a question, a problem that needed to be answered by distinguishing whether
there's time in the day or not time in the day, it's
this is the this was how the question was framed. That the
משנה Mishna, *Mishna* first says לכשיכנס לביתו ניטול על שולחנו *lichshe'yikanes l'beiso
nital al shulchano*. First says when you, you know, take it on
your table, means עלמא דמפסיק *alma d'mafsik*. So the first implication of
the משנה Mishna *Mishna* is interrupt your meal. והדר תני *Vehadar tani*,
and then the משנה Mishna, *Mishna* says לא נטלה שחרית יטול בין
הערביים *lo natla Shacharis yitol bayn haarbayim*. If you didn't take it
in the morning, take it in the afternoon. So why didn't you
take it in the morning? You were supposed to interrupt your meal.
עלמא לא מפסיק *Alma lo mafsik*. So it sounds like you don't
interrupt your meal. So אמר רב ספרא *Amar Rav Safra*, so for
that רב ספרא *Rav Safra* said: לא קשיא הא דאיכא שהות ביום
הא דליכא שהות ביום *lo kashya, ha d'ika sha'os bayom ha d'leika
sha'os bayom*. When you didn't take it in the morning, you didn't
interrupt your morning meal because there was later time in the day.
When the other part in the first part of the משנה mishnah.
*Mishna* it said interrupt your meal, that was like in you're eating
in the afternoon and there won't be time in the day and
that's the difference. Okay, so that's the problem he was coming to
answer that it sounded like from the two parts of the משנה
Mishna *Mishna* a different implicit difference whether you would or wouldn't interrupt
your meal. אמר רבי זירא *Amar Rebbe Zeira*, says רבי זירא *Rebbe
Zeira*: מאי קושיא *mai kushya*? That couldn't have been the problem. דאמר
מצוה Mitzvah, לאפסוקי *D'omar mitzvah l'afsoukay*, because the simple way to read
the משנה Mishna *Mishna* is you should interrupt your meal to take
it, take it on your שולחן *shulchan*, you should. ואי לא *V'ilo*,
but you know what, guess what, not everybody always does what they're
supposed to do. So if you didn't do what you were supposed
to do and you didn't interrupt your meal, ואי לא פסק *v'ilo
pasak*, if you didn't interrupt, יטול בין הערביים *yitol bayn haarbayim*, you
can even take it in the afternoon, שכל היום כשר ללולב *shekol
hayom kasher l'lulav*, the whole day is כשר *kosher*, so the משנה
Mishna. *Mishna* is not a problem. The משנה Mishna *Mishna* just means
you should interrupt your meal, it doesn't tell you what happens if
you don't. And the fact that by מנחה *Mincha* you don't interrupt
to say מנחה *Mincha* is because that's a דרבנן *d'Rabbanan*. So we
have no problems, what do you need to answer? דרבנן *d'Rabbanan* you
don't, דאורייתא *d'Oraisa* you do, end of story. So the גמרא Gemara.
*Gemara* says אלא אמר רבי זירא לעולם כדקאמינא מעיקרא *Ella Amar Rebbe
Zeira l'olam k'dikamina me'ikara*. No, actually there was a problem comparing the
מנחה *Mincha* case, which is דרבנן *d'Rabbanan*, to the לולב lulav, *lulav*
case. That by לולב lulav *lulav* you interrupt and by מנחה *Mincha*
you don't. Why is that a problem again? There's a difference of
דאורייתא דרבנן *d'Oraisa d'Rabbanan*. ודקשיא לך הא דאורייתא הא דרבנן *U'd'kashya lach
ha d'Oraisa ha d'Rabbanan*, doesn't that explain the difference? לולב lulav *lulav*
is biblical you interrupt, מנחה *Mincha* is דרבנן *d'Rabbanan* you don't. No.
הכא ביום טוב שני דרבנן עסקינן *Hacha b'Yom Tov Shayni d'Rabbanan askinan*.
We're talking about יום טוב שני Yom Tov Sheni. *Yom Tov Shayni*
now that again is a phrase that's being used multiple times and
means חול המועד Chol Hamoed, *Chol HaMoed*, it does not mean the
יום טוב שני Yom Tov Sheni *Yom Tov Shayni* of חוץ לארץ
Chutz La'aretz *Chutz La'Aretz*. How do I know it? א *A*, because
of the next line the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is going to say.
It's יום טוב שני Yom Tov Sheni *Yom Tov Shayni* which is
Rabbinic and therefore there is a problem. This is Rabbinic and you
do interrupt and מנחה *Mincha* you don't interrupt. So דייקא נמי, and
I'll prove to you by a close read of the משנה Mishnah.
that we're talking about יום טוב שני. Yom Tov Sheni, How do
you know? נקתני, niktani, מי שבא בדרך. mi sheba baderech. It says
you came back from a journey. What would you be doing traveling
on a journey on יום טוב? Yom Tov? ואין בידו לולב. ve'ein
beyado lulav. דאי
סלקא דעתך di salka da'atach of יום טוב ראשון, Yom Tov Rishon,
מי שרי? mi shari? You can't be traveling on a journey. Now
this גמרא Gemara makes it very clear that יום טוב Yom Tov,
שני means חול המועד, Chol Hamoed, doesn't mean the second day of
יום טוב, Yom Tov. because it says you wouldn't be traveling if
it was יום טוב. Yom Tov. Well guess what? You wouldn't be
traveling if it was יום טוב שני of חוץ לארץ Chutz La'aretz.
either, okay? Besides, the משנה Mishnah isn't talking about חוץ לארץ. So
if we want to say the משנה's Mishna, referring to יום טוב
שני, right, we mean חול המועד, Chol Hamoed, okay? We don't mean
second day יום טוב. And therefore it's Rabbinic, therefore you could be
traveling, and therefore we've got our problem. Why is it that the
משנה, Mishna which is talking about חול המועד, you interrupt in order
to make a—in order to—you interrupt your meal to do a Rabbinic
מצוה? Mitzvah And by מנחה, you don't interrupt in order to do
a Rabbinic מצוה. Mitzvah So what is the difference? And the difference
is whether there's time to do it or not time to do
it. If there will be time to do it, you interrupt—you don't
interrupt. That's the case by מנחה. If you're afraid there won't be
time to do it, you do interrupt. This then becomes the bottom
line principle: by Rabbinic מצוות, Mitzvot, you're not supposed to start certain
activities. You started the activity, do you have to interrupt it? And
the answer is, it matters whether there will be time left to
do it or not.
If there will be time, you don't interrupt. If there won't be
time, you do interrupt. By Biblical מצוות, Mitzvot, then presumably regardless of
whether even if there will be time, it doesn't matter, stop the
activity you're doing to do the Biblical מצוה, mitzvah. to say the
שמע, Shema, to take the לולב lulav on the first day, and
so on. Now even there, there's a question about what would be
if, like, you have a fixed time to do it afterwards, right?
So I normally make sure that I say the שמע—like Shema I
daven early, I didn't say, or let's even say forget that. I
go to a 10 o'clock מנין minyan where I'm going to say
the שמע. Shema. So does that mean as soon as the זמן
קריאת שמע zman krias Shema comes about, I have to interrupt what
I'm doing and saying it? No, you know, there's a difference when
you have, like, a fixed time to do it. But if basically
you should have done it earlier and you didn't, and you're now
in the middle of another activity, so it's already as it were
a pending thing that you should have done and now you started
something else, by a Biblical מצוה mitzvah? you interrupt it in order
to—even if there will be time. By a Rabbinic מצוה mitzvah it
depends whether there will or won't be time. And that's sort of
the conclusion of the גמרא. Gemara So again, the גמרא Gemara. hyper-focuses
on this issue of whether there will or won't be time, but
the bigger חידוש, chiddush, I think, or the bigger point in the
context here is, the assumption you should be making it in the—you
should be doing it in the morning, and you should be doing
it—you should be doing it in the morning and you should be
doing it during הלל, Hallel, and that is the classic time to
be doing it. Okay, and then the next משנה Mishna is going
even—is going even to turn to resuming to the discussion of הלל,
Hallel, because if you look at the next משנה, Mishna. even without
a whole point of לולב, lulav? מי שהיה עבד או אשה או
קטן מקרין אותו, mi shehayah eved o isha o katan makrin oto,
if a slave or woman or minor would be reciting for you
the הלל, Hallel, עונה אחריהם מה שהם אומרים, oneh achareihem mah shehem
omrim, you respond. And the whole next discussion is going to get
to הלל, Hallel, which we'll obviously get to in a minute. But
the point here I want to make is, talk about הלל, Hallel.
waving during הלל, Hallel. oh by the way, if you didn't do
it at the right time and you didn't do it in the,
you know, right place and do it הלל, Hallel, you could even
take לולב lulav, without הלל. Hallel. Let's get back to talking about
הלל. Hallel So it's very clear that the primary locus of taking
of the לולב lulav, is during הלל, Hallel. and again, not just
a statement of, oh first you make the ברכה bracha, and you
shake it, and by the way, you also do it at הלל.
hallel No, it really sounds like the whole idea, the whole context
of doing it is with the הלל hallel. in the שול. shul
So take a look, that's a very important point and you take
a look at the end of this תוספות Tosafot כדי לסתור סברא
זו kedei listor sevora zo back on ל"ז
ע"ב. lamed zayin amud beis. And תוספות Tosafot says this—it's a very
important issue. He says like
this. End of the first middle five lines of the תוספות, Tosafot,
the last word of that line is ובשעת ברכה, ubish'at bracha, לא
מצינו דחייב לנענע בתחלת נטילה. lo matzinu dechayav lina'anea bitchilat netilah.
When you make the ברכה, bracha right, do you have to then—here
he's right now assuming you make the ברכה bracha, not right before
הלל. hallel. You make the ברכה, bracha? do you just hold the
לולב lulav? or do you shake it when you make the—after you
make the ברכה? bracha, אלא מדאמרינן בפרקין ela mid'amrinan b'pirkin קטן היודע
לנענע חייב בלולב katan hayodeia lina'anea chayav belulav that
it says when are you obligated in לולב? lulav When you know
how to shake it, not when you're able to take it. משמע
דמנענע בתחלת הברכה. mashma dimna'anea bitchilat habracha. So the—meaning—meaning a minor, that
you start minors doing מצוות mitzvot when they're able to do the
act of the מצוה. mitzvah, And interestingly, what does it define as
the age which a minor starts—you start educating him to do the
מצוה? mitzvah, When he's able to shake it, not when he's able
to take it. So you see the idea of shaking is central
to the concept of what the act of the מצוה mitzvah, is.
So therefore תוספות Tosafot says, so therefore when you make the ברכה,
bracha. you should have to shake it because that defines— When you
start educating minors to do it, clearly that's a central part of
the act. Again you would be יוצא yotzeh without it, but even
though you technically would be יוצא yotzeh without it, it is central
and therefore תוספות Tosafot says you would do it after you make
the ברכה. bracha אף על פי שאינו יודע לקרות את ההלל. af
al pi she'eino yode'a likros es ha'hallel. Now
תוספות Tosafot makes this other important point though, but this also supports
an idea תוספות Tosafot says that shaking can be significant without the
הלל hallel. because it doesn't say you start teaching a minor to
shake, to take the לולב, lulav when he's able to shake it
and say הלל. hallel You just say when he's able to shake
it. So presumably you can do there's A, shaking is central to
the מצוה, mitzvah but B, can exist independent of הלל. hallel. And
therefore that leads to the possibility that you make the ברכה bracha,
at home and you shake it even though it's not in the
context of shaking it, you know, of shaking it during הלל. hallel.
So there's really three possibilities. The entire thing is just holding on
to it, you know, which בדיעבד bedi'eved is true, but that that's
totally even okay לכתחילה lachatchilah for making the ברכה, bracha, that's not
true because we definitely see shaking as playing a central role. But
is it the shaking during הלל hallel. or not? תוספות Tosafot tries
to prove out from the קטן katan case that you can have
the shaking without the הלל. hallel I'm not exactly sure that's such
a proof because the קטן katan could be in שול shul when
everybody else is saying הלל. hallel He could still do it in
the context of הלל. hallel We're going to enter into a whole
discussion of שומע כעונה, shome'a ke'oneh, listening to the הלל hallel is
like saying it. So to me, just 'cause he doesn't know how
to say הלל hallel doesn't mean that the shaking exists outside of
that context, okay? So anyway,
but then he has one more proof. ועוד מתניא מסכת ברכות בסוף
תפילת השחר, ve'od mi'tanya maseches brachos besof tefillas hashachar, הקדים לצאת לדרך,
hikdim latzeis laderech, if you have to go out to the journey
early, מביאים לו שופר ותוקע לולב ומנענע מגילה וקורא בה, mevi'im lo
shofar vesoke'a lulav u'menane'a megillah ve'korei bah, משמע דמנענע בלא הלל. mashma
de'menane'a belo hallel. It says you had to leave and you couldn't
wait for דאוונינג, you had to leave before שחרית, you make the
ברכה, bracha you shake the לולב, Lulav. and you go on your
journey and you say הלל hallel? when you say it. So again,
nobody is denying that if you don't have a choice you're יוצא.
yotzeh. That's like גארנישט, garnisht, now you came home and you missed
הלל hallel, in שול shul, and you shake it at home. But
the question is even if that's okay בדיעבד, bedi'eved, is the idea
of shaking number one central to the taking of the לולב? The
basic answer is yes. One good evidence is it's how it's originally
phrased in the משנה. Mishna, The other good evidence is is that
the minor
obligation only starts when he's able to do that, number one. And
number two, which shaking, in הלל hallel. or independent of הלל? hallel
Well, it seems that the I would say the strong evidence is
not what תוספות Tosafot is saying, is that the shaking is all
being placed in the context of הלל, hallel. even a minor could
do it in שול shul when they're saying הלל. hallel The fact
that it's possible if you don't have a choice that you do
it separate is not a proof that that's really the לכתחילה. lachatchilah.
So the implications of this are twofold. Number one is if you
do take it out and make the ברכה bracha, before שול, shul
you don't just hold it, you shake it, which is what everybody
does. But the other question is if you agree to תוספות's Tosafot
conclusion, then maybe you take it before going to שול shul and
a lot of people do that, they say like זריזין מקדימין למצוות,
zrizin makdimin le'mitzvos, let's do it first thing in the morning, first
chance that we get. I specifically do not do that and most
people you see don't do that because they all make the ברכה,
bracha you know, in שול and most people are taking it out
and making the ברכה bracha. then. And that is 'cause the stronger
evidence is that certainly as the best
לכתחילה, lachatchilah, it's shaking in the context of הלל hallel. and that's
not just what you do after you've done the מצוה, mitzvah but
that is the way you do the מצוה, mitzvah you know, the
taking of the לולב is the taking and the shaking during הלל.
hallel It's not taking was two hours ago, now we also shake
it. No, the basic idea of the מצוה mitzvah is the shaking
in this context and that certainly is what is more I would
say suggested by the sources and that's why waiting to do the
מצוה mitzvah and to make the ברכה. bracha, So that's all very
powerful especially if you consider the idea that shaking isn't mentioned anywhere
in the תורה. Torah. It just says ולקחתם לכם, u'lekachtem lachem, and
how when we've created this whole הלל hallel context, again maybe because
of this whole idea of אז ירננו עצי היער, az yerannenu atzei
haya'ar, but really sort of broadening the symbolism. What's the לולב about?
So I do want to say one other thing about that, which
is the פסוק pasuk is
ולקחתם לכם ביום הראשון, u'lekachtem lachem bayom harishon, and the end of
the פסוק pasuk is ושמחתם לפני השם אלוקיכם שבעת ימים. u'semachtem lifnei
Hashem Elokeichem shivas yamim. And the idea of שמחה, simcha, right the
whole idea שמחת בית השואבה simchas beis hasho'evah and שמחה simcha connected
to this, and that's תוספות Tosafot quoting that פסוק pasuk of אז
ירננו עצי היער, az yerannenu atzei haya'ar, the trees burst down in
song, it's bringing the joy of the year and you know in
the context the agricultural, the bringing in of all of the harvest
and everything that's been all of the food and so on, and
bringing that joy and expressing that joy to God and using these
symbols as the way of expressing that joy. So that really ties
into הלל. Hallel. Not some prayer to prevent bad rain or not
some idea of we're going to be judged about water, the הלל
Hallel doesn't fit that context so much. The הלל Hallel, fits the
context of the אז ירננו עצי היער az yerannenu atzei haya'ar that
תוספות Tosafot quotes and the ושמחתם לפני השם אלוקיכם. u'semachtem lifnei Hashem
Elokeichem. So again, quite powerful that this becomes a central idea of
the act of the מצוה mitzvah if you consider... technical פסוקים psukim
in the תורה Torah don't speak about this. Okay, so that's really
a very important issue about the nature of the idea of the
shaking of the לולב. Okay so now we go to the משנה
which is now as I've mentioned goes to focus us on the
idea of הלל. Hallel, מי שהיה עבד או אישה או קטן מקרין
אותו. Mi shehaya eved o isha o katan makrin oto. If a
slave or a woman or a minor would recite for you, עונה
אחריהן, oneh achareihen, meaning it was a word-for-word recital. They would say
הללו את ה' כל גויים, Hallu et Hashem kol goyim, you say
הללו את ה' כל גויים. Hallu et Hashem kol goyim. שבחוהו כל
האומים, Shabchuho kol ha'umim, you say שבחוהו כל האומים. Shabchuho kol ha'umim.
So okay, that can work because you don't know it so they
have to be reciting for you word for word. But מה שהן
אומרין, ma shehen omrin, you recite after them what they're saying. ותבוא
לו מאירה, Vetavo lo me'eira, but a curse should fall upon you.
Now why should a curse fall upon you? So רש"י Rashi says
because it displays your ignorance, right? I mean why, what, why aren't
you saying it yourself? Why do you need somebody to recite for
you? Obviously because you're ignorant and therefore that's a real problem that
you don't know how to recite the הלל Hallel. yourself. תוספות Tosafot
says no, it can't just be your ignorance because then it wouldn't
matter whether it was a woman, minor doing it or whether it
was a adult male doing it. Either way,
you're ignorant. תוספות Tosafot says no, actually the problem is is that
you're doing it, you know, if you are already ignorant and not
able to do it, there's a way you do it, well we'll
see, let's finish reading the משנה okay and then I'll sort of
go back and unpack that a little bit more. ותבוא לו מאירה.
Vetavo lo me'eira. אם היה גדול מקרא אותו, Im haya gadol mikra
oto, if an adult was reading for you, then you don't have
to repeat word for word. עונה אחריו הללויה. Oneh acharav Hallelujah. So
basically as what we're going to see in a minute is the
way they would do the recitation in the שול would be the
following. And it's a question whether this would be what everybody would
do or whether it would only be what people who were not
able to say it themselves would do. But basically it was a,
Ashkenazim I hate this, right? I hate this. I never do this,
but whenever there's something responsive for Ashkenazim, we always have to make
sure that we ourselves are saying it and then we answer the
חזן. chazzan. We can't actually just say half of it, maybe because
I don't know, something about maybe because it's printed in the סידור
siddur or something. Anyway but very often in ספרדי Sephardi שולס, shuls,
when they have responsive things, you do your part and the חזן
chazzan does his part. He says this and then you respond, he
says that and you ever respond, you don't have to say everything.
So apparently the way it originally was in terms of the הלל,
Hallel, you know, the חזן chazzan would say הללויה Hallelujah and everybody
would say הללויה. Hallelujah. Then he'd say הללו עבדי ה' Hallu avdei
Hashem and everybody would say הללויה. Hallelujah. And then he'd say הללו
את שם ה' Hallu et shem Hashem and everybody would say הללויה.
Hallelujah. And then he'd say יהי שם ה' מבורך Yehi shem Hashem
mevorach and everybody would say הללויה. Hallelujah. That would be actually a
pretty exciting event to be at, wouldn't it? So that's how, so
you can even imagine that you do that לכתחילה, lechatchila, even if
you know how to do it, why you have to say the
word? Listen to the way you say the הלל, Hallel there's a
reader and a response. Okay, so
but it sounds like it's going to sound in the גמרא Gemara
that this is what you would do if you didn't know what
to say, you would just respond הללויה. Hallelujah. Otherwise you would actually
say the text itself, but not so clear from the משנה. From
the משנה it might be that this is the standard way it
would be done. The you know, the adult would say it, the
המחוייב hamechuyav person, the שליח ציבור Shaliach Tzibbur would say it and
you would say הללויה Hallelujah at various phrases. Okay. מקום שנהגו לכפול
יכפול. Makom shenahagu lichpol yichpol. Places where they used to double up
certain פסוקים, psukim, like אודך ה' כי עניתני Odecha Hashem ki anitani
which we repeat פסוקים, psukim, if that's the מנהג minhag to repeat
certain פסוקים, psukim, you repeat it. לפשוט, Lifshot, if the מנהג minhag
is to just say it straight without doubling it, יפשוט. yifshot. לברך,
Levarech, if there's the מנהג minhag to make a ברכה, bracha. יברך,
yivarech, to make a ברכה. brachah הכל כמנהג המדינה. Hakol keminhag hamedina.
Everything goes by the practice of the place. There are different practices
of exactly how to say the הלל. Hallel? All right, there's not
one rule you follow your different practices, very nice little, you know,
sort of embracing of a diversity of practice. So let's go back
to the issue of that you don't, that it's not an adult
male who's doing the leading but it's a minor or a woman.
So רש"י Rashi says the problem is it displays your ignorance. תוספות
Tosafot says I don't understand, you're ignorant even if an adult male
is doing it, you're ignorant. And the answer might be not necessarily
because if an adult male is doing it and you're saying הללויה,
Hallelujah, you're not, you might be ignorant but you're not displaying your
ignorance. Maybe that's just how you do it, one guy reads and
everyone says הללויה. Hallelujah. The problem is is that if the leader
is not somebody obligated in הלל, Hallel right? Cause a woman and
minor, you know, is not obligated in הלל Hallel because it's like
time bound מצווה mitzvah and so on. I mean it's only דרבנן
but whatever. Then you are displaying your ignorance because then you can't
do the answering הללויה Hallelujah since it's not an official sort of
obligated way of saying it, you know, where they each one is
doing their part, then really they're just feeding you the lines and
it more is displaying your ignorance. So that really seems to be
the idea here. Although again, as I said, תוספות Tosafot says, תוספות
Tosafot feels no, even if an adult male is leading it, you
know, if you know what to say you should say it, so
you know, you'll be displaying your ignorance either way and תוספות Tosafot
therefore just focuses on the idea... using the agency and relying on
somebody who's not obligated and that just looks bad. Now this is
very relevant because of two issues: number one is a hypothetical question
about like nowadays could a woman lead הלל? Hallel, You know, I
mean I'm not suggesting this is whatever, I'm taking this out of
any political context. Let's just talk about it as a pure hypothetical
הלכתי halachic question. So our הלל Hallel is different because our הלל
Hallel is everybody reads from the סידור, siddur, says it for themselves,
there's no responsiveness, nobody is feeding you the lines, so whatever the
issues here are, displaying your ignorance doesn't apply, being obligated and being
מוציא motzi people, it's not the same reality. Everybody's being מוציא motzi
themselves. Is there any הלכתי halachic status to the person leading the
הלל, Hallel. although we do have one section where there is a
responsiveness that is going on, so that's like an interesting question how
to plug in our current realities of saying הלל Hallel to the
assumption here that you need an obligated person to be saying it
and to be leading it. You know, so that's sort of like
one issue. The other reason it's very important is because of the
question of this whole idea of תבוא מארה, tavo me'eira, the role
of having a woman play a role, is that somehow... now again,
in a very male-oriented society, you know, in a patriarchal society, you
know, the sense that, you know, what does it mean for a
man to be ignorant and a woman to be educated was seen
as something deeply
problematic. A that you shouldn't be ignorant, and B particularly a woman
who in those societies was normally the ones that weren't educated and
she knows more than you and that's sort of where those problems
arise. And for some that ties into statements about in the גמרא
Gemara like that, you know, a woman in theory could get an
עליה aliyah but she shouldn't because of כבוד הציבור, kevod hatzibbur, also
sort of connecting it to these possibly to what's going on here
about an issue of demonstrating ignorance and particularly men being ignorant contrasted
to women and what those types of things, you know, again, and
you know, what that would mean in that type of a society.
So this issue about the תבוא מארה, tavo me'eira, the appropriateness of
this type of thing, whether the sense that it's inappropriate in general
for a woman to be playing this role or for you specifically
to be relying, particularly in a case where it's displaying your ignorance,
it can be very relevant to those discussions. And given that we're
almost on פורים, Purim, look at the last line of תוספות, Tosafos,
because the תוספות באמת אמרו, Tosafos Be'emes Amru, look what תוספות Tosafos
says. He says, he says like this:
אי נמי, ei nami, משום דרבים, mishum derabim,
so he's this I don't want to get into the whole discussion,
but he says maybe to have a woman sort of, it's about
leading ברכת המזון, birchas hamazon, even if she is obligated maybe she
shouldn't be leading ברכת המזון birchas hamazon in like a, you know,
where there's a lot of people. משום דרבים זילא בהו מילתא, mishum
derabim zila behu milsa, disrespectful for a woman to be leading ברכת
המזון birchas hamazon in the רבים, rabim, okay? דהרי, deharei, he says
that to explain a discussion he had before. דמגילה, demegillah, דנשים חייבות
בה, denashim chayavos bah, women are obligated in the מגילה. megillah. ופירש
בה"ג, u'peirash Bahag, and the הלכות גדולות Halachos Gedolos says, דאין נשים
מוציאות את הרבים ידי חובתן במגילה, de'ein nashim motzi'os es harabim yedei
chovasan bamegillah, that a woman can't read for men. So why not?
They're equally obligated. So other תוספותים Tosafosim try to explain it based
on this idea that maybe their level of obligation is different, maybe
men are obligated to read the מגילה megillah and women are only
obligated to listen to the מגילה, megillah, but this תוספות Tosafos seems
to make it a purely sort of sociological or appropriateness question. Is
it appropriate for a woman even with the same level of obligation
to be being מוציא motzi men? Okay, so it's just very relevant
for like a lot of discussions that are going on today, how
much is this about demonstrating ignorance and that's the problem? How much
is there a sensitivity, you know, particularly in those types of societies
for women to be playing certain roles and seen as appropriate or
not appropriate? Alright, so that's some of the issues around this whole
point here about women in the משנה. Yes.
Question: The משנה is implying the blessing for הלל Hallel. is a
מנהג? minhag?
We'll get to it in the גמרא. Gemara Okay, let's take a
look. תנו רבנן. tanu rabanan. So, we taught. באמת אמרו, be'emes amru,
in truth we said. בן מברך לאביו ועבד מברך לרבו. ben mevarech
l'aviv v'eved mevarech l'rabo. Now this is about ברכת המזון, birchas hamazon,
that a son can make a ברכה bracha for his father, an
underaged can make one for an adult ברכת המזון, birchas hamazon,
or a slave for the master. Even though they're not obligated. ואישה
מברכת לבעלה, v'ishah mevareches l'ba'alah,
and a woman for her husband. The question whether women are obligated
in ברכת המזון birchas hamazon or not is a whole debate in
the גמרא Gemara in ברכות. Berachos. But at least the first two
clearly are not obligated and they could be מוציא. motzi. אבל אמרו
חכמים, aval amru chachamim, תבוא מארה לאדם שאישה ובנים מברכין לו. tavo
me'eira l'adam she'ishah u'vanim mevarchin lo. Nevertheless
you should be cursed, okay, a curse should come. Now again why?
Same type of a question. So here you could say that it's
simply because they have different levels of obligation, like if a slave
or, I mean the question are women obligated in ברכת המזון, birchas
hamazon, but let's say a minor, a minor who is only rabbinically
obligated, you're biblically obligated, so that's problematic, and the problematic snare because
of different levels of obligation. The question of course is, is that
they are different levels of obligation. Why could the woman be מוציא
motzi the man? You normally can't be מוציא motzi somebody unless you
have the same level of obligation. So the גמרא Gemara there deals
with it, and it might be a case of the following. Right,
could be for example minors are always only rabbinically obligated. As an
adult, I'm obligated biblically to do ברכת המזון, Birkat Hamazon, but only
when I eat biblically only when I eat my fill. If I
just have a כזית, kezayit, my obligation is only rabbinic. So could
be, here's the scenario: my kid ate his fill, I only ate
a כזית, kezayit, so he's rabbinic, I'm rabbinic, but from different perspectives,
and therefore maybe he could be מוציא motzi me. Okay, but nevertheless,
it would be inappropriate because even if technically we now have the
same obligation, I still fundamentally am a person that is in the
biblical category of obligation, and he's a person that's not in the
biblical category. So anyway, here you have a similar issue of curse
should come to you if you do this, but again the question
is why? Is it because of a different level of obligation and
that's the reason and that's the problem? Or is there a problem
that even if the same level of obligation, there's this sense of
inappropriateness? You should be doing it yourself, you know, you shouldn't be
having women and children and slaves, you know, involved in the process.
And again, that raises that question, where exactly does the problem lie
here? Okay, now the גמרא Gemara. says like this. אמר רבא, Rava
says רבא. Rava
הלכתא גבירתא, Hilchata Gevirta,
many important הלכות halachas איכא למשמע מהא מנהגא דהלילא, ika lemishma mei-ha
minhaga de-halleila,
you can infer from the current contemporary practice of הלל. Hallel Okay,
in the time of רבא Rava the practice of הלל Hallel. was
not like it was in the משנה, which is okay because we
said that anyway the משנה was, you know, there were different מנהגים.
minhagim. So the contemporary practice was not like it, but based on
what we do in our current practice, says רבא, Rava you can
infer, we left certain, we have certain things, you know, that we
where we were that were sort of maintained in the current practice
to signal different aspects of the הלכות halachot of הלל. Hallel So
let's take a look. The basic idea is the following. The משנה
lays out a concept of people either don't know or either way
aren't saying the הלל Hallel themselves. The person is leading it and
they're responding הללויה. Hallelujah. Leading it, he says the word, a few
words, הללויה, Hallelujah, a few words, הללויה. Hallelujah. רבא Rava is talking
about a practice where pretty much people were educated or whatever or
the practice shifted and mostly people said all the words themselves. But
nevertheless there were some vestiges of the earlier practice that signaled some
basic הלכות halachot of הלל. Hallel So let's take a look. Okay,
so he says like
this: הוא אומר הללויה והן אומרים הללויה, Hu omer Hallelujah ve-hen omrim
Hallelujah, when it starts, right, the beginning of הלל Hallel is הללויה.
Hallelujah. So the חזן Chazzan הללויה Hallelujah and everybody says הללויה. Hallelujah.
So מכאן, mikan, so even though the rest of הלל Hallel, they're
going to say themselves, here they respond הללויה. Hallelujah. שמצוה לענות הללויה,
She-mitzvah la'anot Hallelujah, that even if you know what you're saying and
you're saying it all yourself, you should be responding הללויה Hallelujah at
least at the beginning. When he says הללויה, Hallelujah, you should say
הללויה. Hallelujah. Okay, הוא אומר הללו עבדי ה׳, Hu omer Hallelu Avdei
Hashem, he says, you know, praise, the servants of God should
praise. והן אומרים הללויה. Ve-hen omrim Hallelujah. Now that's right, the very
first פרק perek of הלל Hallel is right הללויה הללו עבדי ה׳.
Hallelujah Hallelu Avdei Hashem. So he says it, he says הללויה, Hallelujah,
they say הללויה. Hallelujah. He says הללו עבדי ה׳, Hallelu Avdei Hashem,
they say הללויה. Hallelujah. And then everybody goes on and just says
it normally. So the first הללויה Hallelujah is to signal you that
even if you know what you're doing, you have an initial opening
of the הלל Hallel. with הללויה. Hallelujah. What's the second one about?
Since you could just keep on saying it yourself. So he says
מכאן שאם היה גדול מקרא אותו עונה אחריו הללויה. mikan she-im haya
gadol mikra oto oneh acharayv Hallelujah. That's a vestige or that was
maintained to remind people that the הלכה halacha is that if you
don't know how to say the whole הלל, Hallel, that you can
just say הללויה Hallelujah after every phrase, which was the point in
the משנה. He says the phrase, you say הללויה. Hallelujah. So we
maintained that at the very opening even though now again the practice
is everybody says the whole thing, we maintain that at the beginning
of הלל Hallel to signal and to remind us that that was
the way, that's the הלכה, halacha, that if you need to, if
you don't know what you're, if you don't know how to say
it, you can just say הללויה Hallelujah at the very, you know,
at each phrase and that'll be
fine. Okay. הוא אומר הודו לה׳. Hu omer Hodu Lashem. Now when
you get to the הודו לה׳ Hodu Lashem part, he says
הודו לה׳, Hodu Lashem, והן אומרים הודו לה׳. ve-hen omrim Hodu Lashem.
So there's everybody until now after the first הללויהs Hallelujah have been
saying it straight, but when you get to the הודו לה׳, Hodu
Lashem, there is another responsiveness of הודו לה׳, Hodu Lashem, a response
הודו לה׳. Hodu Lashem. מכאן שמצוה לענות ראשי פרקים. Mikan she-mitzvah la'anot
rashei prakim. So you see that there's a מצוה mitzvah to even
again to respond the opening of the chapters. Now what does that
mean? First of all, there are other פרקים prakim between the first
הללויה Hallelujah and the הודו לה׳. Hodu Lashem. Right? If you take
a look at the way we divide the תהלים, Tehillim, I'll open
it again. Right, you have right, over here קיי״ג Kuf Yud Gimmel
is הללויה הללו עבדי ה׳, Hallelujah Hallelu Avdei Hashem, which is what
we started
with. Then בצאת ישראל ממצרים, Bezeit Yisrael MiMitzrayim, then
לא לנו ה׳, Lo Lanu Hashem, then... So תוספות Tosafot says, you
know
what, תוספות Tosafot says maybe the גוים's Goyim division isn't our division
because he didn't have the גוים's Goyim division, but תוספות Tosafot says
maybe they understood that from the initial הללויה Halleluyah all the way
until the הודו להשם Hodu Lashem was one פרק. perek. But they
actually thought that—whereas to us that we have like five פרקים prakim
of תהילים, Tehillim, so just as maybe חז"ל understood it all to
be one big פרק perek and therefore the הודו להשם, Hodu Lashem,
right, is the next פרק perek that you open up with. Now
what does it mean? רש"י Rashi says no. רש"י Rashi says yeah,
we could have done it here, we kept it in one place.
But if you actually were doing the old
way, you would open up each new פרק perek with the beginning
phrase. Now what does it mean that you would open up each
new—מצוה לענות ראשי פרקים? mitzvah la'anot rashei prakim? So רש"י Rashi says
again, this is going back to the way they used to be,
that after every phrase you'd say הללויה, Halleluyah, הללויה Halleluyah after every
phrase. But to signal when you're starting a new פרק, perek, there
would be a moment of shift. So according to רש"י, Rashi, that's
assuming that he had the division we have. So you'd be saying
מושיבי עקרת הבית—everyone Moshivi Akeret Habayis say הללויה. Halleluyah. אם הבנים שמחה—everyone
Em Habanim Smeichah say הללויה. Halleluyah. Then you'd say בצאת ישראל ממצרים
B'tzeit Yisrael MiMitzrayim and now everybody says בצאת ישראל ממצרים B'tzeit Yisrael
MiMitzrayim to signal like we're moving on to the next פרק. perek.
But then you would say בית יעקב מעם לועז Beit Yaakov Me'am
Lo'ez and everybody would say הללויה. Halleluyah. Okay, that's what רש"י Rashi
says. So מצוה לענות ראשי פרקים mitzvah la'anot rashei prakim just means
when you shift to a new פרק, perek, the people the response
is different to signal we're shifting to a new פרק. perek. תוספות
Tosafot suggests something different. תוספות Tosafot says no, you say הללויה Halleluyah
when you're in the first פרק, perek, but when you get to
the second פרק, perek, which according to תוספות Tosafot was הודו להשם
כי טוב. Hodu Lashem Ki Tov. So he says הודו להשם כי
טוב, Hodu Lashem Ki Tov, they say הודו להשם כי טוב. Hodu
Lashem Ki Tov. כי לעולם חסדו, Ki L'olam Chasdo, הודו להשם כי
טוב, Hodu Lashem Ki Tov, right? And then for that פרק, perek,
everything—they're not saying הללויה Halleluyah anymore, they're saying הודו להשם כי טוב,
Hodu Lashem Ki Tov, which is actually great. There are two great
things to be responding, right? Either הללויה Halleluyah or הודו להשם כי
טוב. Hodu Lashem Ki Tov. So in the first section, the responsiveness
is הללויה, Halleluyah, the response is הללויה, Halleluyah, and in the second
section, everybody is responding הודו להשם כי טוב. Hodu Lashem Ki Tov.
I want to be at that הלל. Hallel, That sounds like a
really fun הלל, Hallel doesn't it? So anyway, okay, so according to
רש"י Rashi again, it just means for that opening phrase, but according
to תוספות, Tosafot, it means no, the general responding phrase would be
either the הללויה Halleluyah for the whole first half and the הודו
להשם Hodu Lashem for the second half. But again, in רבא's Rava,
time already they weren't doing that. They were just doing these little
vestiges to remind you that that was the actual original practice. Okay,
so
where were we? Okay, מצוה לענות ראשי פרקים. mitzvah la'anot rashei prakim.
איתמר נמי, itmar nami,
it was also taught, אמר רב חנן בר רבא, amar Rav Chanan
bar Rava, מצוה לענות ראשי פרקים. mitzvah la'anot rashei prakim. It's a
מצוה mitzvah to respond to the beginning of the פרק. perek. הוא
אומר hu omer אנא השם הושיעה נא, Ana Hashem Hoshia Na, והן
אומרים vehen omerim אנא השם הושיעה נא. Ana Hashem Hoshia Na. So
again, if now we're in a time where there's very little of
the responsive reading, we have to indicate what each part that's responsive
is reminding us of. So what's the response that we do by
the אנא השם הושיעה נא Ana Hashem Hoshia Na which is in
the middle of a פרק? perek? It's not הללויה, Halleluyah, it's not
הודו להשם, Hodu Lashem, it's in the middle of a פרק, perek,
why are we doing that? מכאן mikan to remind us of another
thing, שאם היה קטן מקריא אותו, she'im haya katan makri oto, עונין
אחריו מה שהוא אומר, onin achrav mah shehu omer, to say that
there's actually a there is a time where you actually just need
to repeat word for word, not just at the beginning of a
פרק, perek, not a constantly repeating phrase, but actually repeating word for
word what you hear. What would be that case? Where you need
if somebody who's not obligated to be feeding you the lines, then
you have to repeat word for word what you hear. הוא אומר
hu omer אנא השם הצליחה נא Ana Hashem Hatzlicha Na והן אומרים
vehen omerim אנא השם הצליחה נא. Ana Hashem Hatzlicha Na. So what
about the repetition by the אנא השם הצליחה נא? Ana Hashem Hatzlicha
Na? What's that reminding us of? So מכאן mikan שאם בא לכפול
כופל, she'im ba lichfol kofel,
to signal to us that you are allowed to repeat certain פסוקים.
psukim. So we maintain one פסוק passuk that we repeat, so we
maintain little vestiges to remind us of some of these broader practices
even though by רבא's time most of those broader practices had fallen
by the wayside. הוא אומר hu omer ברוך הבא Baruch Haba והן
אומרים vehen omerim בשם השם. B'Shem Hashem.
Now that's interesting because there's a place where they actually did not
say certain words. He said ברוך הבא, Baruch Haba, they didn't say
ברוך הבא. Baruch Haba. They said the second half of the פסוק,
passuk, בשם השם. B'Shem Hashem. Now again, in the older times everybody
would respond הללויה, Halleluyah, הללויה, Halleluyah, they wouldn't say the words. But
this is not הללויה, Halleluyah, this is not הודו להשם, Hodu Lashem,
all it is is you begin a sentence and I end it.
So what does that teach you? It teaches you that because הללויה
Halleluyah could almost be like a type of an אמן. Amen. So
it's one thing to say if you make a ברכה Bracha. and
I say אמן, Amen, I'm יוצא. yotzei. But let's say we said
you say ברוך אתה השם אלקינו מלך העולם Baruch Ata Hashem Elokeinu
Melech Ha'olam and I said בורא פרי העץ. Borei Pri Ha'etz. That's
a different thing. That's not me saying הללויה Halleluyah or me saying
אמן. Amen. You're starting, I'm finishing. Okay, that teaches you— you a
different הלכה. Halacha. What does that teach you? That teaches you מכאן
לשומע כעונה Mikan l'shomeia ke'oneh that if you hear something, it's like
you said it, okay? Because if you said בורא פרי העץ Borei
Pri Haetz and I said אמן, Amen, that doesn't tell you שומע
כעונה. Shomeia Ke'oneh. That says saying אמן Amen is like saying the
ברכה. Bracha. If you say הודו לה' כי טוב Hodu l'Hashem ki
tov and I say הודו לה' Hodu l'Hashem and I'm keep saying
הללויה Hallelujah or הודו לה', Hodu l'Hashem, that's like a type of
an אמן, Amen, right? That's telling you one thing, but it's a
very different thing to tell you that even if you begin and
I end, that even I didn't say an אמן, Amen, it's what
you and I heard the first half, it's like I said I
said it. And that's a very important הלכה Halachic principle of שומע
כעונה. Shomeia Ke'oneh. Now I want to say something even just to
technically understand the words. Normally שומע כעונה Shomeia Ke'oneh is translated as
hearing something is like you said it. But that's not what the
word עונה Oneh means. What does עונה Oneh mean? What does word
עונה Oneh mean? It doesn't mean to say something, or it could
mean ויענו הלוים ואמרו כל העם. Vayaanu haleviim veamru kol haam.
But it means to what? To answer. Right? What would the normal
answer be if you heard something, what would the proper response be?
In this context, what's the proper response when it's being done responsively?
The חזן Chazzan says something, what do you say? הללויה. Hallelujah. Okay,
but let's say you didn't say הללויה. Hallelujah. You just heard it.
Hearing is like doing the response you're supposed to do. That's what
the technical term שומע כעונה Shomeia Ke'oneh means. רמב"ם Rambam has, let's
say a case of a ברכה. Bracha? What's the proper response to
a ברכה? Bracha אמן. Amen. But if you didn't say אמן, Amen,
you're also יוצא Yotzei because hearing it is like saying אמן. Amen.
And the רמב"ם Rambam even creates a hierarchy. רמב"ם Rambam says the
following: העונה אמן כמוציא ברכה מפיו דמי. Haoneh Amen kemotzi bracha mipiv
dami.
If you say אמן, Amen, it's like you verbally said the ברכה
Bracha because saying אמן Amen is sort of like saying ditto, right?
You know, so it's that those words essentially have all the words
to the ברכה Bracha? wrapped into it because you're saying like me
too. Okay, but he says והשומע הרי זה כעונה. Vehashomeia harei zeh
keoneh. So the best is to say אמן,
Amen, but if you just heard it, it's as if you said
אמן, Amen, but it's like one step down.
Did you just hear the ברכה? Bracha. Did you just hear someone
else say אמן?
Amen? No, well that's an interesting question. But let's for now say
the ברכה. Bracha, So you heard the ברכה, Bracha, you're supposed to
be עונה, Oneh, and if you're עונה Oneh and say אמן, Amen,
or in this context הללויה, Hallelujah, it's like you said, it's actually
those words are like the words
you're supposed to say because you actually said something which indicates that
you affirm what's being said. But even if you didn't say the
answer, you just heard it, it's like you said the answer and
that counts. And this is the important הלכה Halachic principle that hearing
works, okay? But it's also important to appreciate the technical meaning of
כעונה Ke'oneh in a context where there would be another type of
a response that we would be more expected. And that's why it's
positioned here. Saying הללויה Hallelujah works, that's an עונה. Oneh. That's saying
and affirming what's being said. Saying the end of a ברכה, you're
not affirming what was said before and you have to say just
listening to it is like I was יוצא. Yotzei. רש"י Rashi therefore
leads this into an important point. רש"י Rashi says if you're in
the middle of דאבנינג davening and they're saying קדיש Kaddish or קדושה
Kedusha and you're in the middle of שמונה עשרה Shmoneh Esrei and
you can't interrupt, just stand silent and listen and it's like you
did the right response to קדיש Kaddish and קדושה Kedusha etc. תוספות
Tosafot says no, because if we really say שומע כעונה Shomeia Ke'oneh
and it's like you responded, then you've interrupted your שמונה עשרה. Shmoneh
Esrei. So תוספות Tosafot take the idea that listening is like responding
in a very literal way. We actually פסקן pasken like רש"י Rashi
that no, it counts that you're יוצא, Yotzei, but it's not like
you actually said it in a sense of interrupting. But this becomes
very important and important for all these ideas like how do we
יוצא Yotzei the מגילה Megilla if there's a מצוה mitzvah to read
it? I'm not reading it, somebody else is reading it. So this
idea that listening is like you did it is a very important
הלכה Halachic principle. Let's just read one more thing. So בעו מיניה
מרבי חייא בר אבא, Bo minei miRebbi Chiya bar Abba, they asked
רבי חייא בר אבא: Rebbi Chiya bar Abba: שמע ולא ענה מהו?
Shama velo ana mahu?
Let's say you heard without responding, which we've already addressed, but maybe
he wasn't part of this earlier discussion. So אמר להו, amar lehu,
so he said back to whoever they were, the people who asked
of him: חכימיא וספריא, Chakimaya vesafraya, a very fascinating way of responding,
the wise people and the סופרים, sofrim, which רש"י Rashi also says
means like the teachers of children, ראשי עמא rashei ama the leaders
of the nation ודרשיא vedarshaya and the דרשנים, darshanim, the expounders, אמרו
amru everyone has said שמע ולא ענה יצא Shama velo ana yatza
hearing without responding you're also יצא. yotza. Just hearing also counts. איתמר
נמי Itmar nami was also taught, אמר רבי שמעון פזי אמר רבי
יהושע בן לוי משום גרפא פרא, amar Rebbi Shimon Pazi amar Rebbi
Yehoshua ben Levi mishum Garpa Para, מניין לשומע כעונה? minayin l'shomeia ke'oneh?
How do you know that listening is like saying? דכתיב את כל
דברי הספר אשר קרא מלך יהודה. Dechsiv, es kol divrei hasefer asher
kara melech Yehuda.
So all the words of the book, this is when they found
a ספר תורה Sefer Torah in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, that
the king, that יאשיהו Yoshiyahu the king of יהודה Yehuda had read.
וכי יאשיהו קרא? Vechie Yoshiyahu kara? Did יאשיהו Yoshiyahu really read them?
ולא שפן קראן? Velo Shafan keraan? שפן Shafan was the one who
read them? דכתיב ויקראהו. Dechsiv, vayikraehu. שפן, Shafan,
שפן Shafan read them in front of the king. אלא מכאן לשומע
כעונה Ela mikan l'shomea k'oneh because he heard it, it was like
he said it. And by the way, this is important again for
the מגילה Megilla idea. It’s not just like he said it, it’s
like he read it, right? So even though there’s a מצוה mitzvah,
to read the מגילה, Megilla, if somebody reads and you hear, it’s
not just like you said the words, it’s like you read the
words. So we see שומע כעונה. shomea k'oneh. So the גמרא Gemara
says ודילמא בתר דקרינהו שפן קרא יאשיהו. v'dilma batar d'karinhu Shafan kara
Yoshiyahu.
How do you know? Maybe after שפן Shafan read them יאשיהו Yoshiyahu
read them even though it wasn’t reported? Maybe he did read them?
אמר רב אחא בר יעקב, Amar Rav Acha bar Yaakov, לא סלקא
דעתך, lo salka datchach, that doesn’t make sense. דכתיב dichshiv יען רך
לבבך ותכנע לפניי yaan rach levavcha vatichna lefanai because your heart was
softened and you humbled yourself before me, I’m sorry, לפני ה׳, lifnei
Hashem, בשמעך beshamacha
when you heard these things. בשמעך, Beshamacha, ולא בקראך. v'lo b'karacha.
You heard them, you didn’t read them. And nevertheless, the verse describes
it as if he read them and this is the principle of
שומע כעונה. shomea k'oneh. Two important points before we end: number one,
תוספות Tosafot says our מנהג minhag of הלל is not even like
רבא's. Right? We don’t do הללויה Halleluya on the הללויה Halleluya at
the beginning. So תוספות Tosafot says okay, but since the גמרא Gemara,
says it’s all based on מנהגים minhagim anyway, there's different מנהגים. minhagim.
So רבא had a different מנהג minhag than the משנה, we have
a different מנהג minhag than רבא, and so they’re acknowledging the different
מנהגים minhagim that we have even different from the beginning of the
גמרא. The other important question is whether there is this idea of
שומע כעונה, shomea k'oneh, is there an idea of that actually saying
it is better than hearing it? Should I better read the מגילה
Megilla myself rather than hear it? Now sometimes there’s a particular מצוה
of doing it בציבור, b'tzibbur, like reading the מגילה, Megilla, so being
part of the ציבור tzibbur definitely outweighs. But let’s say I’m going
to your house. This is what I do at my house: would
anybody like to make קידוש Kiddush or do you want me to
be מוציא? motzi? Yeah, yeah, you just be מוציא. motzi. Okay, but
every now and then somebody says, 'no, I’m going to make קידוש
Kiddush myself.' I don’t know why, I don’t ask, whatever, but some
people actually prefer that because they say when it’s not about a
ציבור tzibbur מצוה like מגילה, Megilla, although even מגילה Megilla you could
be יוצא yotzei when you’re ביחיד, b'yachid, but there’s an element of
בציבור, b'tzibbur, but when it’s fundamentally a more private מצוה, then better
to do it yourself than to do it through hearing somebody else.
There is that question which the גמרא does not address, whether שומע
כעונה shomea k'oneh is as good as עונה. oneh. But again, in
the context of the גמרא, we’re dealing very much with a communal
experience of saying הלל, and therefore clearly it’s not, 'oh, I don’t
want to be יוצא yotzei שומע כעונה, shomea k'oneh, I’m going to
go off to myself.' The whole idea is to be part of
the ציבור. tzibbur. But again, I will also just want to
appreciate what the power is of doing this type of a responsive
הלל and really making it a complete communal
ציבור tzibbur experience. It really feels like we're missing something. We’ve turned
it all into our private little recitals that we're all doing at
the same time and the only bringing together is at the הודו
Hodu moment. But thinking about what this experience was like, I think
is very powerful, it makes us sort of realize something of what
we're missing. Okay.